<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>The Business of Design</title>
  <id>http://localhost:4000</id>
  <link href="http://localhost:4000" />
  <link href="http://localhost:4000/atom.xml" rel="self" />
  <updated>2020-01-31T15:48:14-08:00</updated>
  <rights>Copyright 2020, Julio Ochoa</rights>
  <author>
    <name>Julio Ochoa</name>
  </author>
  
    <entry>
      <title>My MBA Experience</title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/2018/01/13/my-mba-experience/" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I started my MBA program with emphasis in marketing in 2015 with a generous full-ride fellowship from the organization I work for – &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https://www.esri.com&quot;&gt;Esri&lt;/a&gt;. I attended the &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://redlands.edu&quot;&gt;University of Redlands&lt;/a&gt;, which has a gorgeous campus and has been around since 1907. I graduated August 2017, and I feel bittersweet about my graduate program experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On one hand, it has been an incredible learning experience, and I feel that I have broaden my work exponentially. I pushed myself in every course, challenging every project and making it the best it can be. I went above and beyond minimum requirements. In the end, it’s not the piece of paper that matters; it’s what you can do with it that does. Thus far, one of my favorite projects has been: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://blog.julio8a.com/lyft-leveraging-ubers-public-twitter-data-build-marketing-strategies/&quot;&gt;Lyft, leveraging Uber’s public twitter data to build marketing strategies&lt;/a&gt;, from my marketing analytics class. It focuses on leveraging twitter and R with sentiment analysis for marketing strategies. While attending the program, I have met some great, fun people who are dedicated like myself. The greatest benefit has been the business knowledge I was lacking as a designer. I feel so much more conformable with numbers and actually prefer them now. One of my favorite classes was statistics. Statistics? I know right, who would like statistics? Stats proved to me how critical it is, especially when applied to data. It is invaluable when it comes to making a decision. Even better, decisions with a set of probability distributions of success, now that is powerful. I will probably go into detailed aspects of the program later… Long story short, going to grad school was one of the best decision I could have made. Therefore, thank you Esri.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, I noticed how little effort some students put into the projects, but still graduate and obtain good grades throughout the program. To me, it waters down the degree and makes it less valuable. Makes me feel that anybody can obtain this. All you have to do is do the bare minimum or turn something in and you have a decent grade. Moreover, there was a student in my cohort who rarely attended any classes – I’d see this person at the first class and the last for final presentations, so attendance is not so important to the school either. The professors do not push or challenge the students either. On some classes, it was open-ended and it was up to the students to perform. Bad idea. Most of the students in my cohort always asked for the minimum and deliver that. You can have a really good project and get a 4.0. You can also have mediocre projects or very had projects and will still be a 3.5 or higher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, I have had an amazing experience at the University of Redlands pursuing my Masters in Business Administration with an emphasis in Marketing. I have challenged myself and created a good network. Going back to school for an MBA has been one of the best decisions I have ever made. However, I wish the school, program, professors, projects, etc. were more challenging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s next for me? As far as education I will continue to learn and consider a DBA. Some of the concepts I leaned towards the end of the program include data analytics and data science. I was really impressed with the capabilities of &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https://www.r-project.org/&quot;&gt;R&lt;/a&gt;. Therefore, I will focus on that for a bit after school since there is much to be learned. It will be good to focus on algorithms, machine learning, and deep learning. Most importantly, I need to ensure that I apply all the skills learned in the MBA program to my work and personal life on a daily basis and continue to learn as life is a never-ending learning process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In December 2017, I was promoted from Senior UI Designer to Design Program Manager. Going from the lead UI designer for one of our key products, Operations Dashboard for ArcGIS to focusing on global design at Esri and building our internal &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https://forumone.com/ideas/what-is-design-system&quot;&gt;design system&lt;/a&gt;. My new role’s objectives includes building a design system and visual language for our 60+ products and digital marketing efforts. Moreover, ensure harmony and consistency within our platform of product and services. It’s a new position for the company, which will bring it’s set of challenges, but also opportunities.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/2018/01/13/my-mba-experience/</id>
      <updated>2018-01-13T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Julio Ochoa</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Ethical Dilemma – Google’s data collection: geographic results</title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/06/03/Ethical-Dilemma-Google-data-collection-geographic-results/" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;“We Know Where You Are. We Know Where You’ve Been. We Can More or Less Know What You’re Thinking About” (Saint, Business Insider). A quote by Google’s ex-CEO and now executive chairman of Alphabet, Google’s parent company. Google, which needs little to no introduction to the average person, specializes in organizing the world’s information and making it universally accessible and useful. As of today, Google’s market capitalization exceeds five hundred billion USD, making it one of the most valuable publicly traded companies in the world. Google specializes in different disciples in a range of industries and is most known for its powerful search engine capabilities and customer oriented results. In this essay I will discuss Google’s practices of controlling what is visible on user’s screens, and challenge the ethics of this principle. First, I will cover Google’s practices for gather user information. Secondly, I will specifically focus on the geographic aspect of search results. Next, I will review Google’s intentions and motivations. Finally, I’ll review how geographic information search results might affect Google and its users in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google is a dominant player when it comes to connecting users to information they’re most likely looking for in a vast sea of unrelated data. Their search engine is extremely fast and precise. One of the notes I made from looking at Google’s homepage is that it’s simple and has minimalistic design. From my perspective, Google’s homepage design was built as a possible deception to the user, by keeping it very simple as if nothing else is going on their homepage. The complete opposite is happening when a user input a search query and one of the most robust, intelligent and complicated search engine algorithms in the world takes control. As Tene states in his journal What Google Knows: Privacy and Internet Search Engines, “we adore Google for its simple, modest-looking interface masking a hyper-complicated algorithm, which is the very essence of online ingenuity” (Tene, 2). Moreover, there is nothing on Google homepage that states or notifies the users of the actions Google will take once they submit a search query. Google analyzes and stores every query a person enters, which users might not know about. It also creates a log of searches and can directly connect that log to a specific user via IP address, which is a unique number assigned to a user’s computer. Therefore, Google can add new searches to a user’s log by identifying the users IP address. Overtime, this will create a vast database for every user. With the amount of servers in Google’s possession, every search query is stored; no matter how long, short, silly, repetitive, distinct, admirable, terrifying, etc. This information will then be used to predict future searches, which Google has complete control over. So, what will Google show to its users?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to data collection, in my opinion Google should follow Deontology principles and the duty to do the right thing for its users. People who submit search queries should be informed by Google about storage practices and usage of data collection. I strongly believe that users should be notified before using Google’s services and accept the terms and conditions. Therefore, a user can make a decision whether they still want to perform a search through Google or perform a search with a competitor. This will provide the users with a frame of choice, which they didn’t have before. By adding a disclaimer or privacy notification on the Google homepage, which they currently don’t have, users could make an informed decision. This will follow deontology principles and conceive informed, educated and comfortable users. In a practical sense, Google is collecting data from billions of users simultaneously all over the world. It is their duty to inform every single user about their storing practices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A secondary concept, closely related to deontology is Jeffrey Pfeffer’s concept of people, profits, and perspective. “Getting good financial numbers at the cost of people is not only not rewarded but not tolerated for very long, reflecting the company’s belief that in the long run, the numbers will decline if people are not being treated properly” (Pfeffer 402). Whether that’s the physical or mental well-being of employees or customers, having a profit-driven approach will eventually hurt the organization. Again, this will be directly connected to having informed users who know about the data collection and storage practices of Google. By treating people well, they will, in turn, become loyal and returning customers that will happily use Google’s services, because they feel secure and respected. Creating informed users will benefit Google in the long run as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the contrary, one can argue: what if someone is planning to do something evil, such as a terrorist attack? In this case, it would be beneficial for Google not to display the privacy disclaimer on their homepage. If Google displayed a data collection notification the people planning the attack would not use Google’s search engine. They wouldn’t want to give away their geographic location. From a quick experiment on the Google homepage, I typed but did not press enter: ‘planning a ter’. Interestingly enough the first suggestion from Google was, ‘planning a terrorist attack’, followed by, ‘planning a terraced garden’ followed by, ‘planning a territory’ and finally, ‘planning a short-term weight management program’. The first suggestion from Google is connected to harming innocent people, why did this come up? I’ve never searched for ‘planning a terrorist attack’. This would mean that Google is suggesting this query based on common and reoccurring searches, whether playful or serious. Google stores these searches and an IP address to the computer who searched it and Google knows who they are. Therefore, when it comes to user privacy nobody is exempt, even people who are attempting to hide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2015, there were about 8.6 billion devices compared to 7.3 billion people living on this earth. There are now more mobile devices than people, according to a study by a US market research company. By 2018 there is projected to be 12.1 billion devices worldwide (Radicati, 2). In the every growing world of technology, which is changing every month, week or every day, new advancements are constantly overriding each other. Everyone competing to make a mark in the world and be part of history. At times, some will cross ethical boundaries in order to positively change the world. This is the ethical test I bring to Google and their results practices based on a person’s geographic location. If you don’t allow Google to track your location, for example opening a web page and you are asked via a notification at the bottom of the browser: “www.google.com wants to use your devices location.” Even if I deny this request from Google, they still approximate location based on the following components to help provide users with the most relevant results: IP Address, location history, and recent locations searched (Google, Inc). Therefore, Google will still try to find your current location and determine search results, even after being denied access to specific GPS (Global Positioning System) location. For example, searching for ‘finance’ in a place such as New York City, NY, will return results showing brokerage and investments firms. From first glance and based on geographic location this makes sense. New York City is one of the top financial geographic areas in the world. If I search for finance in a different geographic location like San Bernardino, CA, then Google will generate different results. The search query will then return web pages for financial help, such as bankruptcy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Immanuel Kant’s categorical imperative principles, Google’s practices are not ethically sound and do not follow the ethical code. Kant’s categorical imperatives capture the essence of morality, stating that unless the principle can be universalized, it is immoral (Bowie 57). Therefore, we confront Google geographic search results practices by comparing the results for different geographic location. In this case, Google is acting immorally by showing different results to two different users based on their geographic location. If Google were to follow Kant’s principles, they should be able to show investment results to people in San Bernardino, just as they should be able to show financial help websites to people in New York City. Google’s practices of user discrimination based on his or hers location are unethical. From personal experience, I lived in San Bernardino for one year and I am an investor. Based on Google’s location practices, this is unjust to me not to show me investment results via its search engine. Google is not providing me with the tools and investment opportunities as with someone who lives in New York City. I can then conclude that I will not have the same resources to make the best investment decisions. On a larger scale, this is a more serious problem. If Google doesn’t show investment websites and solutions to people in San Bernardino, those people cannot easily learn about investment or make good economical decisions for themselves or their families. This creates the never ending circle and plays a role in the classic presumption that poor people will always live among the poor and rich people will live among the rich.  Google is a tool contributing to this dilemma.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the contrary, Stuart Mills argues the opposite with utilitarianism and its core principles of the greater good for the greatest number of people. “Utilitarianism is outcome-oriented; its goal is to bring about the greatest happiness” (Gustafson 79). In continuation with using the example of New York City and San Bernardino, we can see that Google is attempting to please everyone. No matter where they reside. Whether someone lives in Krakow, Poland or Sydney, Australia, Google utilizes stored information as well as geographic location of individuals to help them find answers they are looking for; in turn, this will maximize global user utility. Therefore, it is important and some can say vital for Google to have information about its users. Google can now generate informed and fairly accurate results that will serve users best. It is clear that Google attempts to bring utility to as many people as possible. Google’s objective is to satisfy people’s individual search needs. Jeremy Bentham, in contrast to Kant, argues, “This utilitarian principle is simply that the right thing to do is to do whatever brings the most please to the most people” (Gustafson 79). Therefore, Google is paralleled to utilitarian principles: attempting to bring happiness to the greatest number of people, and it requires an advanced algorithmic system to maximize this utility for 7.2 billion individuals. In the case of Google, Mills brings a good challenge to Kant’s categorical imperatives, providing adjusted searches and geographic location based results, which will benefit everyone. If Google wouldn’t follow utilitarian principles and showed everyone the same results, not as many people would be satisfied or happy. This is because it might serve them best based on their location, situation or environment, which Google accounts for when they perform a search query. An example of utilitarianism, contradicting Kant’s categorical imperatives: Imagine you are exploring a city, far from home and a dental emergency arises. It wouldn’t be practical for Google to show you every dental office in the country or the world. In this case, it makes perfect sense for Google to find your location and show results for the nearest dental office. It would be difficult and painful if you had to search through a global list of results. An old yellow page book is a good analog example of a global list, everyone gets the same thing. As oppose to Google’s new algorithm, which is very targeted towards specific environments and situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe that Google does the correct thing from the utilitarian perspective. Everyone has different wants, needs, and desires. Google does its best to understand them and provide solutions for users as individuals, based on their individual needs, while attempting to please as many people as possible. Personally, I want access to the right information at the right time. In today’s world and with a new generation of tech-savvy individuals, everyone wants information now. Nobody wants to spend any time searching, they want to look at their phone and get exactly what they want when they need it, which is why Google is such a profitable organization. They satisfy consumer needs and give users what they want. Moreover, in Q3 of 2015 Google revenue resulted to 18.7 billion and net income of 3.97 billion (Dipane). With this fiscal capital, they can employee the most creative, innovative, and forward thinking minds. Leading to Google’s extremely secure system. The web browser provides several security-related configurable options. These include remembering form data and passwords; accepting cookies; displaying security warnings; loading images; enabling JavaScript; blocking pop-ups (Shabtai). Great security then evokes the act of trust with customers. I fully trust Google with my information and know that my personal and private information is secure. I don’t believe that Kant’s categorical imperatives make much sense in Google’s case, because having a global list that everyone will see, no matter who they are or where they are, does not seem effective. Users would have a very difficult time finding the correct content for them. This would also be very time consuming for most users, as they would spend time looking through all results. Another component to geographic results, which I personally find extremely beneficial to myself based on my exploratory lifestyle is discovery: when exploring a new city, I don’t have time to explore the entire area manually. Google’s location results will provide me with a list of results near me, which I am attracted to based on my preferences and previous search history. I can now better allocate my time during my trip. Because of my exploratory nature, Google will also introduce me to places I never knew about, which presents me with new opportunities and possibly find new places I didn’t know about before. This practice will also advertise and empower local businesses.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google practice the separation of results based on geographic location, because this is the demand from users which fuels Google’s profit motive. Google’s objective is to generate clicks, which in return create revenue. Google’s number one priority is to satisfy shareholder needs, which is to generate profits. Therefore, it is in their best interest to generate as much profits as possible. Again, pointing back to Kant’s philosophies: “Truly moral actions cannot be contaminated by motives of self-interest” (Bowie 65). Bowie further explains that even the best actions of the best corporations, such as Google, are not truly moral because of the profit objective. Therefore, if Google was unable to produce profits, it would not be able to operate. Many corporations, including Google, tend to focus their efforts on the bottom line. Kantian philosophy contradicts these principles, stating that profits can be enhanced if we do not focus exclusively on the bottom line (Bowie 66). A great example is the case study of Merck &amp;amp; Co., Inc. choosing to produce a drug that would help people in poor countries with river blindness disease. These victims had limited ability to pay even a small amount of drugs or treatment (Donaldson 254). Merck &amp;amp; Co., Inc. knowing that production of the medication to treat river blindness would not return profits decided to produce anyways for the greater good of people. These actions followed the principles of Immanuel Kant, the duty to do the right thing and prioritize the good of others. Most organizations place profits over the well being of people because it is a primal instinct to survive and over time a symptom of greed. At the end of the day, their decision is profit driven, not people driven.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“I just want to point out that utilitarianism shares with Kant that special appeal to anal compulsives in its doting over principles and rationalization and its neglect of individual responsibility” (Solomon 69). Organizations are made up of people that have the necessity for their individual well being. “Each of us is ultimately lonely. In the end, it’s up to each of us and each of us alone to figure out who we are and who we are not, and to act more or less consistently on those conclusions” (Solomon 66). Aristotle’s principles are based on individualism, everyone looking out for themselves. In the case of Google as one entity, individualism falls parallel with their current practices of self interest. If Google was unable to produce profits, then it would not operate or provide service to its users. Therefore, making profits the primary goal for existence is acceptable under Aristotle’s principles and virtue theory. Understandably, if Google has no funds to operate then it cannot help its users find appropriate information. This theory of individualism states that we should bring out the best in ourselves and our enterprise. Therefore, by bringing out the best in ourselves it will bring out the best in the organization, benefiting users and shareholders. How does this affect users and location based search results? It is to Google’s benefit to show the most relevant results to the users based on their context and location. For example, if the user is in Hollywood, California, possible results might be: Hollywood Walk of Fame, Chinese Theater, Hollywood Sign, Hollywood Wax Museum, etc. Therefore, because these are nearby attractions, it is beneficial for Google to display these results for people in this area. In turn, these clicks will return profits for Google through click advertisements. This action will benefit all parties involved. It benefits customers by having many nearby attraction options and related results based on their search query and Google, by generating advertisement revenue from the advertisement click. All the individual contributors of Google, each have a unique skill set to make robust and secure product. Most importantly to Google, the shareholders who are the owners of the company and gain from the profits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My belief is in virtue theory and the quest for one to do the best for oneself. In its basic and raw form at the end of the day, when we look in the mirror or in our final hour of life we only have ourselves. Our own being is an absolute, no matter what we do as individuals or collective, we will always have ourselves, this is guaranteed. Therefore, we should pursue our own goals, aspirations and happiness. Perusing the goals of the collective does not guarantee the success and happiness of ourselves. On the contrary, if we pursue our own goals and ambitions then we’re guaranteed happiness with the success of obtaining it, because they are ours, they belong to us. All parties pursuing their own interest at their greatest potential will in turn benefit everyone else, as the concept of Adam Smith’s invisible hand states. The guidance and benefit society receives when individuals act in their own self-interest when trying to make money (Smith 349). Meaning that if Google pursuit its own interest, for example making geographic results as robust as possible, then that will provide the best results for the users and in turn generate many clicks. Finally, this will then generate profits for Google. Therefore, by Google acting in their self-interest everyone is satisfied, specifically the customers who will have a great experience when performing searches in specific geographic locations. Google pursuing their self-interest will create value for the customers, who at the time of their search are also interested in their best self-interest based on the specific circumstances. As humans, our primal instincts are in our self interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the ever changing world of technology, Google as well as other organizations will face difficult ethical dilemmas. In the future of big data and understanding user’s behavior will only continue to grow, it is something that will not be going away any time soon. This brings us to our concern of informing users of what is being geographically collected, tracked and search results presented. As more and more corporations continue to gather our personal information, the question we must ask ourselves is: who can be trusted? The prospects for digital and geographic location privatization is looking dim, with more and more technology companies entering the world of geographic information systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this paper, I’ve reviewed who Google is and their role in the always changing technology and geolocation industry, then assessed Google’s methods for collection information and data in order to provide users with the best results based on environment and context. Next, I analyzed Google’s geographic search results from the perspective of Immanuel Kant, Stuart Mills and my personal position. Furthermore, I evaluated Google’s operating methods of profit driven vs. user driven, and applied concepts of Aristotle’s virtue theory and Kant’s theory. Finally, I quickly reviewed the future of data collection and the unavoidable usage of the internet and privacy concerns. Google is a vastly robust and powered organization, and has established trust within its community of users to provide the best service possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Donaldson, Thomas, Patricia H. Werhane Ethical Issues in Business A philosophical Approach Eighth Edition. Upper Saddle River, New Jersery: Pearson Prentice Hall, 2008. Print.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Google, Inc. “Change Your Location on Google.” – Search Help. N.p., n.d. Web. 09 Apr. 2016. &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https://support.google.com/websearch/answer/179386?hl=en&quot;&gt;https://support.google.com/websearch/answer/179386?hl=en&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dipane, Jared. Google Announces Q3 2015 Results: $18.7 Billion in Revenue, $3.97 Billion Net Income. Android Central. N.p., 22 Oct. 2015. Web. 09 Apr. 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Radicati, Sara. Mobile Statistics Report, 2014-2018 THE RADICATI GROUP, INC. A TECHNOLOGY MARKET RESEARCH FIRM PALO ALTO, CA, USA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schneier, Bruce. Data and Goliath: The Hidden Battles to Capture Your Data and Control Your World. New York: W.W. Norton, 2015. Print.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shabtai, Asaf, et al. Google Android: A State-of-the-Art Review of Security Mechanisms December 2009&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Smith, Adam. AN INQUIRY INTO THE NATURE AND CAUSES OF THE WEALTH OF NATIONS MetaLibri Digital Library, 2007. Digital
Tene, Omer. What Google Knows: Privacy and Internet Search Engines (October 1, 2007). Utah Law Review, Forthcoming. SSRN: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://ssrn.com/abstract=1021490&quot;&gt;http://ssrn.com/abstract=1021490&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.1021490&quot;&gt;http://dx.doi.org/10.2139/ssrn.1021490&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/06/03/Ethical-Dilemma-Google-data-collection-geographic-results/</id>
      <updated>2017-06-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Julio Ochoa</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Lyft, leveraging Uber’s public twitter data to build marketing strategies</title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/04/30/lyft-uber-r/" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;h2 id=&quot;executive-summary&quot;&gt;Executive Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This report explores how Lyft can leverage Uber’s public twitter data to build marketing strategies. As the two largest private taxi service providers, competition is fierce and data analytics is key as a competitive advantage. Therefore, I probe the possibility and exploiting Uber’s public data and leveraging it as Lyft’s strength. The following section explains the research objectives in exploring public twitter data and outlining the key success metrics. Secondly, I’ll review the research plan and methodology. This part is vital in ensuring high-quality quantitative data for analysis. Next, I’ll assess the data findings. This is the core section of this research project, which will validate the plan and methodology. It will determine if the endeavor of utilizing public twitter data to aid the marketing strategy process is credible. Finally, if my research and experiment are successful, I will recommend marketing strategies based on my data findings.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;research-objective&quot;&gt;Research Objective&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Research question: How can Lyft use twitter sentiment analysis and geolocation to understand what Uber’s customers are saying and build a marketing strategy in specific geographic areas? For example, what are New York City customers saying on twitter about Uber? If there are negative sentiments, how can Lyft use them to build marketing strategies in New York City to acquire these Uber followers or customers?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The objective is to determine if Lyft can leverage Uber’s negative public twitter data and build marketing strategies based on the findings. Our goal is to use Uber’s weaknesses as Lyft strengths. Moreover, understand Uber’s customer base, learn what makes them tick and see what other findings I can utilize in Lyft’s marketing endeavors. This methodology is one tool for building marketing strategies, if proven successful it should still be considered along with other marketing tools and never used as a stand-alone strategy. Furthermore, this research should allow me to build strategies to acquire Uber customers who experience similar frustrations. Based on the findings, I should be able to find patterns of behavior and frustrations of Uber customers/followers. Therefore, allowing me to approach them with a solution to their problem by using our services. This research will also allow me to compare what commonalities of differences from experiences Lyft customers face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;success-metrics&quot;&gt;Success Metrics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To provide Lyft with successful marketing strategies, I must obtain a large sample size of tweets from New York City. This sample size should reflect a good number of negative tweets, which will allow me to build a robust marketing strategy and successfully target frustrated Uber customers/followers. The analysis should provide a cluster of similar information, which will be the key metric for a recommended marketing strategy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;research-plan-and-methodology&quot;&gt;Research plan and methodology&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The core of the research plan and methodology is focused on utilizing R and the twitteR package by Jeff Gentry to download the dataset of tweets (twitteR package doc: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/twitteR/twitteR.pdf&quot;&gt;https://cran.r-project.org/web/packages/twitteR/twitteR.pdf&lt;/a&gt;). Moreover, the twitteR package connects to the twitter API for downloading tweets (for more information on the twitter API look here: (&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https://dev.twitter.com/overview/api&quot;&gt;https://dev.twitter.com/overview/api&lt;/a&gt;). The objective is to collect a minimum of 100,000 tweets containing &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;@uber&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code class=&quot;highlighter-rouge&quot;&gt;#uber&lt;/code&gt;. However, the tweets collected, not all will be from New York City, they will contain retweets and will not have a sentiment analysis score attached to each tweet. Therefore, by utilizing R, I will clean up the dataset to only assess the tweets from New York City with a negative sentiment, not including retweets. To conduct the sentiment analysis, I will use Minqing Hu and Bing Liu opinion-lexicon library. This library contains two .txt files, one with positive keywords and another with negative keywords. I will run my tweet text through these two files to obtain a sentiment analysis score. Negative sentiments scores will have a negative numeric value and positive scores will have a positive numeric value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are the steps I will take using R to clean up the data. The outcome will be negative sentiment tweets (not including retweets) from New York City. Data clean-up process leveraging R to clean up includes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remove retweets.
Remove tweets which don’t have a New York City location.
Use Minqing Hu and Bing Liu opinion-lexicon library to categorize New York City tweets in 3 categories: neutral, positive and negative.
Use R to analyze negative sentiment tweets from New York City.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-findings-and-cleanup&quot;&gt;Data findings and cleanup&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I collected 136,615 tweets between March 21st, 2017 and April 16th, 2017; each tweet contains these attributes:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/posts/uber-lyft/twitter-table.png&quot; alt=&quot;Twitter API output table&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, not all attributes are necessary for my analysis. Therefore, only these attributes were analyzed: text, favoriteCount, created, ScreenName, retweetCount, longitude and latitude.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the issues I encountered was a large amount of missing latitude and longitude values. When users send a new tweet, they must have location enabled on their tweet for me to get the latitude and longitude values once downloaded, which was not a common practice amount the 136,615 tweets I collected. Therefore, I used the Google Maps Geocode API to find user location based on screenName. Moreover, I could attribute tweet location based on user profile location.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/posts/uber-lyft/collection-of-tweets.png&quot; alt=&quot;Collection of tweets - totals&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After removing all retweets, I was left with 79,947 tweets (58.52%) of the original 136,615 tweets. Next, I ran a sentiment analysis to determine which tweets had a neutral, negative and positive sentiment. This left us with 19,046 (13.94%) tweets with a negative sentiment value. Finally, I used Google Maps Geocoding API (more info here: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/maps/documentation/geocoding/intro&quot;&gt;https://developers.google.com/maps/documentation/geocoding/intro&lt;/a&gt;)  to geocode all negative sentiment tweets. Additionally, from this list I filter out all the New York City tweets, this left me with 1,165 negative sentiment tweets (0.85% of total collection). Final data cleanup output includes 1,165 tweets of the 136,615 tweets. Finally, I now have all New York City location tweets, which are not retweeted and have a negative sentiment value. The next step is data analysis and looking for patters and consumer behaviors to help Lyft build marketing strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;data-analysis--negative-tweets&quot;&gt;Data analysis – Negative Tweets&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this portion of the analysis we look at descriptive statistics for sentiment score, retweets, favorited and truncated data from tweets. From the filtered down dataset, all sentiment scores have a negative value since they are only negative sentiment tweets. All negative tweets have an average sentiment score of –1.35. Moreover, tweets were favorited an average of 1.2 times and retweeted an average of 0.7 times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/posts/uber-lyft/basic-statistics.png&quot; alt=&quot;Data analysis - Basic statistics&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, here is a visual plot displaying the sentiment score by date of tweets. It is an even distribution of tweets over time. Moreover, keep in mind that range is –5 (very bad) to –1 (not so bad).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/posts/uber-lyft/tweet-distribution-plot.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Data analysis - Visual plot&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through a word cloud we conduct further analysis into the text with most frequent words appearing in the negative tweets dataset. Visually, we can identify the most common word used in the negative tweets is ‘driver’. This leads me to believe that followers (customers) are having issues with Uber drivers. In the section, I’ll go into a further analysis of the most frequent words by day. Other noticeable words include: crash, ubersupport, charge, report, fuck, problem, service, and cancel. These are words to note when it comes to Uber’s service and customer experiences, as we will analyze in detail later in this paper.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/posts/uber-lyft/word-cloud.png&quot; alt=&quot;Data analysis - Word cloud&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All negative tweets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/posts/uber-lyft/negative-tweets-table.png&quot; alt=&quot;Negative tweets - table&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I collected Uber’s public twitter data from March 22st 2017 to April 16th 2017. Below is a histogram of the data collected, 1 bin represents one day. Therefore, we have 25 bins from March 22st to April 16th:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/posts/uber-lyft/negative-tweets-bar-chart.jpeg&quot; alt=&quot;Negative tweets - chart&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From the histogram above we can notice a few days when Uber had many negative tweets: March 25th, 28th, 30th and April 6th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;March 24th – an Uber car testing self-driving technology flipped onto its side in Tempe, Arizona, after being hit by another car. Thereafter, Uber suspended their self-driving car program in Arizona on the 25th. Clearly, the news made it to New York City where Uber followers (and potential customers) tweeted about the crash. From analyzing the tweets from March 25th, here are the main keywords tweeted that day in descending order based on frequency of appearance: Crash, driver, car, suspends, program. Since the Uber self-driving car crash took national news, New York City tweeters believe this was an important event since it was the most tweeted negative event from our histogram.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;March 28th – Uber releases its first ever diversity report. 15% of Uber’s technical workers are women, the same as twitter and just under Facebook (17%) and Slack (24%). According to O’Brien, “Uber’s culture — and its treatment of female employees — has been in the spotlight after a former female engineer alleged sexism and harassment at the company last month” (O’Brien, 2017, para 3). Moreover, this prompted Uber’s CEO Travis Kalanick to call for an urgent investigation, which is expected to conclude at the end of April 2017. Finally, when it comes to ethnic diversity, Uber has zero technical leaders who are African American or Hispanic/Latino. That’s only bumped up slightly when looking at non-technical leadership positions: (3.7% are African American and 1.2% Hispanic/Latino). Therefore, causing negative sentiment on Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;March 30th – New York lawmakers met to discuss state budget. This included an expansion of Uber upstate. Moreover, the bill included a possible 4% tax increase on rides. Additionally, Uber insures their drivers up to $150,000. Therefore, the bill will permit large cities to prevent companies like Uber from operating if they choose. My assessment would be that Uber customers would be opposed to this bill and have a negative sentiment towards it since paying more for their Uber rides would add up and be costly in the long run as possibility of tax increases come into play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;April 6th – By far was the most noticeable event when I researched the day on Uber’s news calendar. “The young Bronx woman who threatened to call police and falsely accuse an Uber driver of rape has been banned from the app for life, a spokesperson says” (Perez, 2017, para. 1). The female passenger accosted the male Uber driver for almost 9 minutes, Dash cam footage was released of this event. Additionally, not only did she threaten to report the driver for rape, the enraged woman was also caught on video saying she would punch herself in the face and tell cops he did it. Though this event had negative sentiment on Twitter, it was not targeted towards Uber specifically. It was negative sentiment against the woman who was accosting an ordinary responsible Uber driver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;March 25th, 28th, 30th and April 6th had high frequency of negative tweets. I compared these high frequency dates with news events about Uber. Moreover, to support to my analysis above here is a table with the top 5 frequency of words for each day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/posts/uber-lyft/negative-tweets-frequency.png&quot; alt=&quot;Negative tweets - frequency table&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, lifecycle of frequency words by date:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/posts/uber-lyft/negative-tweets-frequency-chart.png&quot; alt=&quot;Negative tweets - frequency chart&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, notice that the keywords that are related to the news events are not the primary negative frequency word. The only case where this is true is March 25th. Even though we could extract a specific news event from each date with a high frequency of negative tweets, it seems that the ‘driver’ or ‘driving’ is still the primary concern with tweeters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we answer the question of who are the influencers in NYC. Below is a bar chart with users who were retweeted the most and had many favorited tweets:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/posts/uber-lyft/users-by-retweet.png&quot; alt=&quot;Negative tweets - Users by retweet&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The biggest influencer in New York City is The Root. The Root is an American online magazine of African American culture launched on January 28, 2008 by Henry Louis Gates Jr. and Donald E. Graham. Their Twitter account has over 90,000 tweets and over 317,000 followers. Here is table with the tweets from TheRoot:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/posts/uber-lyft/users-by-retweet-table.png&quot; alt=&quot;Negative tweets - Users by retweet table&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All three tweets are related to the April 6th event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Next, we look at the relationship of the negative retweets and favorited tweets in New York City. After conducting a regression analysis with the sample size of 1,165, there is a positive correlation between retweet count and favorite count. Retweet count was utilized as the independent variable, with favorite count being the dependent variable:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/posts/uber-lyft/negative-tweets-regression.png&quot; alt=&quot;Negative tweets - Regression&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From our regression analysis, we can see that there is a positive correlation between retweetCount and FavoriteCount (67%). Therefore, as retweet count increases, favorite counts will also increase. The overall regression model was significant with, F (1, 1163) = 937.4, p &amp;lt; .001, R2 = .45. Moreover, our model indicates that retweet count is a good predictor of favorite count. Meaning 45% of the variation in favorite count can be explained by the retweet count. Furthermore, we can now use this model to predict favorite counts based on retweet counts. For example, if a tweet is retweeted 108 times, what is the probable favorite count? We can identity the favoriteCount by using the regression equation:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Y = a + bx&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;FavoriteCount = 0.62 + .79(108) = 85.94&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, we can conclude that if a tweet is retweeted 108 times, it will be favorited 86 times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we look at the negative tweets with the lowest score. Aside from all the news events Uber faced, customers also seem to be having issues with drivers, prices and Uber’s transaction system:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/posts/uber-lyft/negative-tweets-details.png&quot; alt=&quot;Negative tweets - Detailed descriptions&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;conclusion&quot;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, from all data collected there was a small percentage of negative tweets from New York City (0.85%). Negative tweets had an average score of –1.354. I discovered that the biggest influencer was TheRoot, an online magazine. Also, there was a correlation between retweet count and favorite count. Retweet count can explain 45% of the favorite count. The majority of negative tweets gathered were relate news events. Therefore, more difficult to dissect what issues New York City customers are uniquely facing when it comes to negative sentiment towards Uber’s services. News events are national and maybe global. Therefore, not unique to our geographic area of interest. However, clearly displayed in the WordCloud and frequency of most used words in the negative NYC tweets, I discovered the high frequency words of ‘driver’ and ‘driving’. In addition, in the last portion of the analysis I discovered customer’s frustrations with Uber drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;recommendation&quot;&gt;Recommendation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aside from the recommendation to stay out of major PR disaster like the ones Uber is constantly facing, I would recommend a marketing strategy advertise Lyft drivers. In the last portion of our data analysis I discovered that customers were facing very difficult issues with Uber drivers. Therefore, the recommendation is to advertise Lyft’s driver’s and their friendliness with customers in New York City would be taken well. When it comes to transportations services I believe the driver is the most important aspect of providing good experiences for customers. Drivers have the responsibility to understand the customer and how they should interact with them. Customers can be busy people not wanting to be disturbed during their ride or then can be talkative and wanting to interact with someone. This responsibility should be left to the driver to determine what type of customers they have and act appropriately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, advertising of the Lyft hiring vetting process could also prove successful in New York City. Especially with the customers who had difficulty with drivers. If potential customers can understand that Lyft doesn’t just hire anybody, but good quality drivers it can bring frustrated Uber customers to Lyft services. “…some Uber drivers in major cities like NYC work 19 hours in a day” (Bliss, 2016, para. 10). This is a good explanation why some drivers get easily frustrated with customers. They are tired and at times sleep deprived. Therefore, short tempered. Lyft should take advantage of Uber’s bad drivers in NYC. In comparison to Uber, “With Lyft, every 14 hours you’re in driver mode requires you to take six hours off” (Bliss, 2016, para. 9). Clearly, this can result in more well-rested drivers. Therefore, friendly drivers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, my strongest recommendation would be to send reconciliation tweets to users who experience bad events with Uber. Most importantly, we can set up automated algorithms, which can send coupons or $5 off to tweets with a negative sentiment value equal to or below -3 containing strings such as “going to Lyft”, “switch to Lyft” or any other keywords indicating that customers want to make a just over to Lyft from Uber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;reference&quot;&gt;Reference&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bliss, Jeanne. (2016). Why You Should Love Lyft More Than Uber. Customer Bliss. Retrieved from: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://www.customerbliss.com/love-lyft-uber/&quot;&gt;http://www.customerbliss.com/love-lyft-uber/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bing Liu, Minqing Hu and Junsheng Cheng. “Opinion Observer: Analyzing and Comparing Opinions on the Web.” Proceedings of the 14th International World Wide Web conference (WWW-2005), May 10-14,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2005, Chiba, Japan. McKinley, Jesse. (2017). In Albany, Glimpses of Budget as Federal Cuts and Deadlines Loom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The New York Times. Retrieved from: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2017/03/30/nyregion/federal-cuts-new-york-state-budget-andrew-m-cuomo.html?_r=0&quot;&gt;https://www.nytimes.com/2017/03/30/nyregion/federal-cuts-new-york-state-budget-andrew-m-cuomo.html?_r=0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Minqing Hu and Bing Liu. “Mining and Summarizing Customer Reviews.” Proceedings of the ACM SIGKDD International Conference on Knowledge Discovery and Data Mining (KDD-2004), Aug 22-25, 2004, Seattle, Washington, USA,&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;O’Brien, Sara A. (2017). Amid Turmoil, Uber releases first diversity report. CNN. Retrieved from: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://money.cnn.com/2017/03/28/technology/uber-diversity-report/&quot;&gt;http://money.cnn.com/2017/03/28/technology/uber-diversity-report/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Perez, Chris. (2017). Uber bans rider for life over threat to accuse driver of rape. New York Post. Retrieved from: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://nypost.com/2017/04/06/uber-bans-rider-for-life-over-threat-to-accuse-driver-of-rape/&quot;&gt;http://nypost.com/2017/04/06/uber-bans-rider-for-life-over-threat-to-accuse-driver-of-rape/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reuters. (2017). Uber suspends self-driving car program after Arizona crash. CNBC. Retrieved from: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://www.cnbc.com/2017/03/26/uber-self-driving-car-arizona-crash-suspended.html&quot;&gt;http://www.cnbc.com/2017/03/26/uber-self-driving-car-arizona-crash-suspended.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/04/30/lyft-uber-r/</id>
      <updated>2017-04-30T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Julio Ochoa</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Opportunity Analysis – Virtual Workout Groups in the United States</title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/04/16/home-workout/" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;During undergrad (2010), I had this idea to create virtual GYMs where people can work out from home with their friends as a social event and workout sessions with a personal trainer. In short, recreated the GYM at home with little to no equipment. Fellow students and instructors encouraged me to pursue this idea, build it out and make something out of it. Not so motivated or believing much in the idea, I skimped out. A few years later realizing that at the same time in 2010, two Standford grad students were pursuing this same endeavor and by 2012 they had raised more than $1 million in funding and were in acquisition talks with weight watchers. Regret sunk in. Anyways, here’s my opportunity analysis on the fitness industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;market-analysis&quot;&gt;Market Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This analysis will examine opportunities in the fitness industry, with a specific focus on virtualized, social and live exercise experiences for women. Consumers of this service are looking for an at-home workout program that fits into their lives. Women have a smaller interest in weight training over men, which is why this virtualized workout organization is tailored towards women (no equipment needed). The service will provide live workout sessions with 1 instructor, which will guide and adapt to session attendees. Each session will allow up to 5 participants to create a social experience, for example, friends who want to work out together. Cameras and real-time feeds will enrich the workout experience for participants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;quantitative-data&quot;&gt;Quantitative Data&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As of 2013, in the United States female population of 25–39 years of age between was 30,739,000 (census.gov).
64% of women over 20 years of age are overweight (niddk.nih.gov).
54 million Americans paid gym membership fees in 2014 (franchisehelp.com).
50% of people who begin structured exercise programs (gyms) drop out within 6 months (Mullen, Whaley, p. 1).
A study of 1,000 women found that 64% of those who run, attend a gym or group exercise classes with friends will push themselves harder than if they went alone. (dailymail.co.uk)
Qualities Important in Fitness Activity. Factors: 1 – 5 rating (survey of 233 participants)
Convenience &amp;amp; Staffing – Mean: 4.29. Standard Deviation: 0.67
Time Related – Mean: 4.14. Standard Deviation: 0.79
Extra Amenities – Mean: 3.08. Standard Deviation: 0.90 (Mullen, Whaley, p. 29)
Qualitative Data
Social: Today, fitness is very popular. One out of five Americans has a gym membership (dailymail.co.uk). Moreover, people don’t like to exercise alone, which is why an online service that brings the social experience of exercise to their homes is desired. According to Virgin Active Health Clubs research, people perform better when they are with friends versus alone. Customers are mainly looking for convenience and time-related qualities in gyms. Many people are very busy and can’t always make it out to the gym. Our services will allow customers to make their own workout schedule and all from the convenience of their own home, with the ability to work out with friends that are five blocks apart or even thousand miles away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Health: With obese and overweight population level at its highest of all times, people are looking for ways to get back into shape. With more than two-thirds of the population considered overweight or obese, there is no doubt that American’s health has never been worse. Overweight refers to an excess amount of body weight that may come from muscles, bone, fat, and water with BMI higher than 25 but less than 29.9. Obesity refers to an excess amount of body fat with BMI over 30, with extreme obesity starting at BMI 40. Both being overweight or obese can cause serious risk – type 2 diabetes, heart disease, high blood pressure, and much more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;industry-analysis&quot;&gt;Industry Analysis&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;quantitative-data-1&quot;&gt;Quantitative Data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gym memberships have grown 18.6% between 2008 and 2014. (franchisehelp.com)
There’s 34,000 fitness centers in America with an increase of 6.4% over 2013. (franchisehelp.com)
2014 fitness centers’ revenue of $24.2 billion also had a sharp 7.4% increase over $22.4 billion in 2013. (franchisehelp.com)
According to the Bureau of Labor Statistics, these fitness and recreational sports centers employed 533,200 people in 2014, and jobs are expected to grow 8% by 2024. (franchisehelp.com)
The average monthly cost of a gym membership is $58&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;qualitative-data&quot;&gt;Qualitative Data&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Competition: The fitness industry is fierce. From local gyms like 24 Hour Fitness, Planet Fitness, Gold’s GYM, Anytime Fitness, etc. to some existing virtualized gyms like Daily Burn and Wello. The industry is fairly defined in the sense of physical gym location, but the competition in virtual exercising experiences is just starting. With continual advances in technology virtualization, it is spreading in all aspects, including working out from home. “Market demand is strong, and finding success will come down to finding the type of fitness business that will work for your local community” (franchisehelp.com). Technology and devices are becoming more ubiquitous than ever, which will grant an opportunity to home digital gyms and easy access to healthy exercise from customers’ homes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Threat of new entry: Working out from home with a live trainer and some friends is a threat to existing gyms which have physical locations. Costs significantly decrease when there is no real estate involved, electric bill, water bill, equipment, etc. Physical location requires space and equipment rental or purchase, all which creates large overhead to production. Virtual gyms do not have a physical location – the technological infrastructure lives inside a few servers, which take up little to no physical real estate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Technology: Over the decades, technology has changed many industries. It is critical to assess the impact of new technologies and utilize them accordingly. The photography film industry was destroyed by a shift in technology – digital cameras. There’s a possibility that technology can transform homes into virtual gyms, where people will no longer have to drive into a physical location. Though I doubt that digital home gyms will ever completely replace physical gyms, they will still penetrate the fitness industry’s market share. Today, there are more and more apps with pre-recorded workouts for the home. Technology will enable convenient workout schedules for customers, which according to the survey conducted Mullen and Whaley is seen as one of the most valuable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;references:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dailymail.co.uk. (2013). Looking for a fitnessboost? Workout with a friend – research shows that women train harder with an exercise partner. &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/health/article-2263099/Looking-fitness-boost-Workout-friend–research-shows-women-train-harder-exercise-partner.html&quot;&gt;http://www.dailymail.co.uk/health/article-2263099/Looking-fitness-boost-Workout-friend–research-shows-women-train-harder-exercise-partner.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fitness Industry Analysis 2016 – Cost &amp;amp; Trends &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https://www.franchisehelp.com/industry-reports/fitness-industry-report/&quot;&gt;https://www.franchisehelp.com/industry-reports/fitness-industry-report/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases: Overweight and Obesity Statistics. Data from the National Health and Nutrition Examination Survey, 2009–2010 Retried from: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health statistics/Pages/overweight-obesity-statistics.aspx &quot;&gt;https://www.niddk.nih.gov/health-information/health statistics/Pages/overweight-obesity-statistics.aspx&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;U.S. Census Bureau, Current Population Survey, Annual Social and Economic Supplement, 2013. Internet release date: March 2016. Retrieved: September 2016.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;S.P. Mullen, D.E. Whaley (2010). Age, Gender, and Fitness Club Membership: Factors Related to Initial Involvement and Sustained Participation. University of Virginia.&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/04/16/home-workout/</id>
      <updated>2017-04-16T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Julio Ochoa</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Geographic Information Systems (GIS) And The Insurance Industry </title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/04/04/GIS-insurance/" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;“Insurance is a product that both the seller and buyer hope is never actually used” (Author Unknown) is a revealing statement about the insurance industry, where both sellers and buyers approach with caution. Insurance companies want to maximize premium profits with as little risk as possible. In this essay, I will explore how GIS (Geographic Information Systems) play a key role in the insurance industry. First, I will talk about how insurance companies can utilize GIS for risk analytics and leveraging risk. Second, I will explore natural disasters and how insurance companies can quickly respond to events, determine claim costs and notify policyholders. Finally, I will discuss a more commonly use of GIS in real estate insurance. With home buyers swarming the market after the 2008 housing collapse, home insurance companies are back at quickly estimating and determining insurance premiums.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;risk-analytics&quot;&gt;Risk Analytics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The primary objective for insurance companies is to eliminate risk and have a clear picture of all variables involved in making a decision. The more data an insurance company can obtain, the more choices and opportunities will be presented. From automobile insurance to home insurance, data is the key to forecasting events, “These include such information as proximity to hazards and emergency services, traffic patterns, commute routes, assets and crime” (Richardson 2011, para 1). Richardson brings up traffic patterns, which clearly affect automotive insurance companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By analyzing traffic patterns and flows, auto insurance companies can make better decisions when providing policies to customers. A specific method to determine traffic congestions and heavy traffic areas are heat maps. A heat map is a graphical representation of data where the individual values are represented as colors, which is then overlaid on a map. Automotive insurance companies will also have a more detailed report from a number of cars in the congested areas per day, to the time there is no traffic. All of this data can help insurance companies make informed decisions on premiums. For example, an insurance company may charge a larger premium to someone living in Los Angeles, which has a population of about 4 million people. In contrast, the premium for the same coverage can be substantially low for someone residing in Coachella, CA, the population of 45 thousand. There are fewer cars on the road in Coachella. Therefore, the chances of an accident are reduced. All this information can be visualized on a map and analyzed to minimize risk. Heat maps based on traffic patterns are just one component of GIS in the automobile insurance industry. There are many other components that play a role, such as demographics, driving distances (home to work), weather conditions, driver’s age, years of driving experience, etc. Below is an example of a heat map displaying heavy traffic areas in a city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/posts/GIS/heatmap.png&quot; alt=&quot;Heatmap example&quot; /&gt;
&lt;small&gt;Google developers – Heatmaps example &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https://developers.google.com/maps/documentation/javascript/examples/layer-heatmap&quot;&gt;https://developers.google.com/maps/documentation/javascript/examples/layer-heatmap&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;natural-disasters&quot;&gt;Natural Disasters&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“According to a global insurance study, worldwide economic losses from natural disasters in 2010 totaled $194 billion. Disasters can damage infrastructure, interrupt production and significantly impact private sector’s financial performance.” (Groenfeldt, 2012, p. 2. Para. 6). Natural Disasters are mainly unavoidable. Esri (Environmental Systems Research Institute) – the largest GIS software company – helps insurance companies manage risk. During my research, I found an Esri developed an application that helps insurance companies with risk management (Insurance Risk Management Demo: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://webapps cdn.esri.com/Apps/StepByStep/&quot;&gt;http://webapps cdn.esri.com/Apps/StepByStep/&lt;/a&gt;). Using the scenario of a hurricane approaching southern Florida I will demonstrate how the application works. Let’s assume that an insurance company has many policyholders. With Esri’s risk management app, the first step is to visualize all their policyholders on a map. Second, find where the majority concentration of policyholders reside. Third, the insurance company can now display where the highest valued homes are. Fourth, overlay the areas the hurricane will affect the most with different colors representing different intensities. Finally, the insurance company can estimate which homes will be affected by the hurricane and what the potential claim value will be. They can also inform their at-risk policyholders to help protect their family and property. In this example, the insurance company will notify all policyholder which will be in an area that will have more than 3ft of water, due to a hurricane.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hurricane example visualization:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/posts/GIS/insurance-demo.png&quot; alt=&quot;Insurance risk management demo&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Insurance Risk Management Demo &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://webapps-cdn.esri.com/Apps/StepByStep/&quot;&gt;http://webapps-cdn.esri.com/Apps/StepByStep/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Insurance Risk Management tools are critical in the insurance industry, as they can provide accurate estimates of property damages and claims. It is also a good tool to keep track of where all the policyholders reside relative to each other, and where there is a large concentration of risk. As technology continues to evolve and raw data is appended as variables to processes, the more accurate predictions and forecasts will become, making the decision-making process easier and creating more precise insurance premium estimates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;purchasing-home-insurance&quot;&gt;Purchasing Home Insurance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Where” is the popular word in GIS, identifying all relevant information of a specific geographic location. When home insurance companies are assessing premiums, it is critical for them to understand the context of the geographic location of the customer. Some of the variables that come into play during the assessment process are hazardous zones: earthquakes, floods, volcanic, hurricanes, tornadoes, fires, etc. For example, areas that are more prone to hurricanes and floods will have a much higher insurance premium than locations that are not. Alongside with other factors: location demographics, crime rates, population density, etc. – there are just a few geographic components that affect insurance premiums and decisions about ensuring customers. Rightfully so, if a high risk for claims exists, premiums would be higher. GIS enables insurance companies to take this analysis and better serve their customers. Below is an example of historical earthquakes in California, which evokes higher insurance premiums for earthquake insurance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/blog/assets/img/posts/GIS/home-values.png&quot; alt=&quot;Global historical hazards&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;small&gt;Global Historical Hazards (Pacific Disaster Center)
&lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://www.arcgis.com/home/item.html?id=0fa97960564248288ad121a00f77cc57&quot;&gt;http://www.arcgis.com/home/item.html?id=0fa97960564248288ad121a00f77cc57&lt;/a&gt;&lt;small&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/small&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GIS is essential and a critical component for insurance companies, since they do depend much on location and location analytics. GIS enables insurance companies to make informed decisions and properly assess, maintain, manage, monitor, forecast and predict events which affect them directly and their customers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this essay, I reviewed how insurance companies analyze risk and leverage it to make decisions. Next, I discussed the effects of natural disasters and how insurance companies utilize GIS to respond to events such as hurricanes. Finally, I reviewed the process of insurance companies utilizing GIS when ensuring homeowners and all the array of variables that are involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Environmental Systems Research Institute (Esri). Insurance Industry. Retrieved From: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://www.esri.com/industries/insurance&quot;&gt;http://www.esri.com/industries/insurance&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Environmental Systems Research Institute. Insurance Risk Management Demo. Retrieved from: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://webapps-cdn.esri.com/Apps/StepByStep/&quot;&gt;http://webapps-cdn.esri.com/Apps/StepByStep/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Groenfeldt, Tom. (2012). Zurich Insures Supplier Risk As Climate Change Increases Natural Disasters. Forbes. Retrieved from: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/sites/tomgroenfeldt/2012/05/10/zurich-insures-supplier-risk-as-climate-change-increases-natural-disasters/#590df4014ce0&quot;&gt;http://www.forbes.com/sites/tomgroenfeldt/2012/05/10/zurich-insures-supplier-risk-as-climate-change-increases-natural-disasters/#590df4014ce0&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Richardson, Karen. (2011). Insurer Uses GIS for More Accurate Risk Analysis. Directions Magazine. Retrieved from: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://www.directionsmag.com/entry/insurer-uses-gis-for-more-accurate-risk-analysis/180325&quot;&gt;http://www.directionsmag.com/entry/insurer-uses-gis-for-more-accurate-risk-analysis/180325&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/04/04/GIS-insurance/</id>
      <updated>2017-04-04T00:00:00-07:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Julio Ochoa</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Strategies for Job Enrichment </title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/2017/02/20/happy-workplace/" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;“For workers who are really prospering in their jobs, work is likely to be a lot like play” (Hackman et all, 1975, p. 60). This concept jumped off the page, because at the company by which I’m currently employed I feel that I play and have fun every day. I believe that in today’s business world the more our employees feel like they play, the more productive, efficient, satisfied, excited, optimistic, energetic they will feel about their jobs. In this essay, I will discuss what job satisfaction is and how it affects individual employees. Next, I’ll review some of the benefits and pitfalls of job enrichment. Finally, I will explain how job enrichments currently affect me at Esri (my current position) and how I can implement job enrichment going forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-job-enrichment&quot;&gt;What is job enrichment?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Herzberg concluded that true employee satisfaction rests in a fulfilling job experience – more commonly known as job enrichment or vertical job loading.” (Kulpa, 2015, para 3). Kulpa touches on a strong point here about employee satisfaction, the fuller and exciting job an employee has, the greater the experience and motivation they will obtain. Employee satisfaction and job enrichment are critical to today’s workforce, where competition is extremely intense. How I see it, satisfied employees tend to be more efficient, effective and overall maximize their performance. Hackman, Oldham, Janson and Purdy break down motivation and job satisfaction into three components: 1) Experience meaningfulness 2) experience responsibility 3) knowledge of results.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Experience meaningfulness – “The individual must perceive his work as worthwhile and important by some system of value he accepts” (Hackman et all, 1975, p. 60). For example, a soccer player who likes to play pickup games at his local park, enjoys playing the game to better his skills and obtain a healthy lifestyle through exercise. This activity is meaningful and valuable to him because he enjoys soccer and a healthy lifestyle. This activity is integrated as part of his value system and there is an objective from participating in the soccer activities. Experience responsibility – “He must believe that he personally is accountable for the outcomes of his efforts” (Hackman et all, 1975, p. 60). In continuation with the soccer player example, he knows that he alone is responsible for participating in the soccer games. If he does not attend the pickup games he must accept the consequences of a reduction in his soccer abilities as well as a diminished healthy lifestyle. It is his responsibility to maintain his schedule and be responsible. If he maintains this principle he will consistently be dependable and reliable for the games.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Knowledge of results – “he must be able to determine, on some fairly regular basis, whether or not the outcomes of his work are satisfactory.” (Hackman et all, 1975, p. 60). The soccer player must constantly be measuring his objectives and results to determine effectiveness. His goal is to better his skills and be healthy. He can effectively track his progress in multiple ways: see improvement in speed, ball control, passing accuracy etc. He can also track his health by observing his well-being, monitoring his body fat and weight. It is critical to be aware of the results, as this will allow a determination of what is working and what is not, which will provide informed decisions and adjustments to the soccer player’s behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;arguments-for-job-enrichment&quot;&gt;Arguments for job enrichment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a plain and simple form factor, job enrichment can reduce boredom. “Employees get bored with the mundane day-to-day tasks they have to complete” (Brookins, n.d, para 3). Job enrichment can add a variety of duties and tasks that are new to employees, which in turn can reduce their workplace boredom. It also changes their current activities at their job, which can add a level of adventure exploration and fun. Job enrichment will also expand the knowledge, learning capabilities and skills of employees. Boredom and repetitiveness can lead to stagnation. Reducing boredom will keep the employee from conducting repetitive tasks, which can make the day feel very long&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Who excels with a great depth of task may gain recognition, which can lead to company awards and incentives, or even a promotion within the company” (Brookins, n.d, para 4). Recognition is a large and promising component of job enrichment. As Brookins stated, recognition can be a promising driver for achievement and increased performance within employees. Job enrichment can also be a good driver to identify employee’s strengths and weaknesses, as a form of recognizing individual characteristics of employees. Recognition can also lead to noticing and molding new potential leaders who show promising characteristics. Recognition is an important factor to continual good behavior and performance. When one employee is recognized, others will observe and mimic this behavior resulting in it surrounding subordinate improvements. In general, people want to be respected and valued, recognition enables this feeling in subordinates improving job satisfaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;arguments-against-job-enrichment&quot;&gt;Arguments against job enrichment&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“When employees are given a greater depth of tasks through job enrichment, they may not be skilled or experienced in the new tasks they’re asked to perform” (Brookins, n.d., para 6). Job enrichment can be a very powerful motivator for subordinates, but the lack of training and skills can be a huge disadvantage and lead to lower productivity. On the side of the employee, this can lead to confusion, loss of direction, loss of motivation and frustration. Employees should also be equipped when taking on new assignments or challenging tasks. On the side of the organization lack of training and skills can cause more damage. This can lead to poor production of product or service and possible dissatisfied customers or bad experiences. Organizations must be careful when attempting to add job enrichment into employees’ daily jobs because if the employee is not prepared, it can cost the organization money.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When enriching the job of employees, it comes with exploration and new tasks, as well as completing their currently assigned work. This can lead to increase workloads. “While some employees may be able to immediately re-prioritize their time and tasks, some may initially experience difficulties getting adjusted with their new responsibilities. (Brookins, n.d., para 7). In my opinion adapting to new environments as well as new tasks is critical to perform effectively. The faster we can adapt to the environment or tasks, the faster we can start solving problems. The issue with adapting quickly is the excess or work an employee has. This at times can make it very challenging to adapt and take on the new tasks, which in turn will disable the employee from performing properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-i-would-use-it&quot;&gt;How I would use it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;bring much value to organizations. It is also a good form to establish stars and potential leaders. As a leader, I will use components such as recognition to motivate employees to perform at their best. This will allow them to demonstrate their abilities and create some healthy competition within their teams. Enriching one individual’s job will, in turn, motivate others to do the same, creating a chain effect that will spur motivation, satisfaction, and performance within teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will also utilize job enrichment techniques to create an innovative environment. “When an employee’s level of responsibility increases, and she gets the opportunity to try new tasks, it’s inevitable that she will learn new skills” (Brookins, n.d., para 2). I see learning as a critical component to growth, communication, and innovation. Job enrichment will enable employees to learn new skills, which will result in personal grown. These new found skills will then empower employees to become innovators within their respected fields.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Job enrichment can empower individuals to push the boundaries of their capabilities, allowing them to learn, grow and be innovative. In today’s competitive marketplace it is essential that organization produce the best and innovative products to market. Job enrichment will provide extraordinary outcomes if utilized properly. In this essay, I’ve covered what job enrichments entails. Next, I reviewed concepts in favor of job enrichments and concepts against it. Finally, I discussed some techniques I can apply to my everyday job which will enable individuals to perform at their best utilizing job enrichment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Brookins, Miranda. (n.d.). The Advantages &amp;amp; Disadvantages of Job Enrichment. Smallbusiness.chron.com. Retrieved from: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://smallbusiness.chron.com/advantages disadvantages-job-enrichment-11960.html&quot;&gt;http://smallbusiness.chron.com/advantages disadvantages-job-enrichment-11960.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hackman, J.R., Oldham G., Janson, R., Purdy K. (1975). A New Strategy for Job Enrichment. California Management Review, Vol. 17 No. 4, SUMMER 1975; (pp. 57-71)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kulpa, Jason. (2015). To Motivate Employees, Find a Balance Between Job Enrichment and Job Enlargement. Entreprenuer.com Retrieved from &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/242816&quot;&gt;https://www.entrepreneur.com/article/242816&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/2017/02/20/happy-workplace/</id>
      <updated>2017-02-20T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Julio Ochoa</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>The Power of Virtual Teams</title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/27/virtual-teams/" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;“Today’s financial woes have forced many companies to pick members of project teams from across various global locations and have them communicate virtually – by phone, e-mail and videoconference – thereby saving both time and money” (Meyer, 2010, Forbes). This bold statement from Mayer is stating the rapid growth of virtual teams conceived to reduce cost, bring new ideas or have continual production twenty-four seven around the world. In this essay I will review what virtual teams consist of in the always growing technology industry. Moreover, I will discuss arguments in favor and against virtual teams. Finally, I will review how can I use this research and implement it into my daily activities at the company I work for – Esri, which consist of some virtual teams.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-are-virtual-teams&quot;&gt;What are virtual teams?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A virtual team (also known as a geographically dispersed team, distributed team, or remote team) is a group of individuals who work across time, space and organizational boundaries with links strengthened by webs of communication technology. For example, at Esri we have a team of designers, developers and product engineers which reside across US with some of the team members working in Redlands, California and some in Portland, Maine. Our main form of communication is e-mail, instant messaging platform called Slack, phone and virtual conferences. According to Ferrazzi, “The appeal of forming virtual teams is clear. Employees can manage their work and personal lives more flexibly, and they have the opportunity to interact with colleagues around the world. Companies can use the best and lowest-cost global talent and significantly reduce their real estate costs” (Ferrazzi, 2014, Harvard Business Review). I see flexibility of virtual teams as a large benefit for both organizations as well as employees. Employees can see an increase in work satisfaction because of flexible work schedule. Organizations can observe lower costs which are an attributing factor for virtual teams. Reducing office space will in turn avoid leasing a building to fill employees with, which will reduce cost, affect the bottom line and allow the organization to allocate those funds towards hiring more employees or purchasing other assets. The key component of virtual teams is communication. If there is a minimal error or misalignment – it may cost the organization a large sum or money from misallocated use of time and resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;arguments-in-favor-of-virtual-teams&quot;&gt;Arguments in favor of virtual teams&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We’ve found that successful virtual team players all have a few things in common: good communication skills, high emotional intelligence, an ability to work independently, and the resilience to recover from the snafus that inevitably arise” (Ferrazzi, Harvard Business Review). The components motioned my Ferrazzi are critical to effective virtual teams. Successful proper use of virtual teams can return high dividends for organizations. Some of arguments in favor of virtual teams would be: Quick turnaround of projects, robust and creative ideas cause of multicultural teams and reduction in total cost due to outsourcing certain roles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a software company having developers in the United States, China, and London will fill all the gaps of development time. Therefore, the U.S. team will start developing a portion of an application, once they clock out – the London team can take over, then the China team. This will maximize the development time of the application causing a quick turnaround on projects and building software, while using the overlap time to communicate the work done and being passed on from one team to another. This will allow all teams to contribute to an application cycling through work and the development process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organizations will hire and retain individuals who can make a big difference in an organization and who can bring unique and valuable experiences. Chand from yourarticlelibrary.com states, “Virtual teams allow firms to expand their potential labour markets enabling them to hire and retain the best people regardless of their physical locations” (Chad, yourarticlelibrary.com). Based on Chad’s statement, organizations can hire the best minds no matter where they are. From my experience working at Esri – one of the largest privately owned internet software companies – it is difficult to attract talented professionals from across the world to relocate to Redlands, CA. On the other hand, creating a virtual team eliminates this problem entirely by allowing the company to hire individuals from all over the globe without the need of relocation. There is then one centralized location to work, the world wide web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Companies can use the best and lowest-cost global talent and significantly reduce their real estate costs” (Ferrazzi, Harvard Business Review). Virtual teams do not require buildings or offices, which is one of the most expensive aspects of operating a business. Moreover, organizations can hire extremely talented individuals from other countries often for half the salary of U.S. employees. Ferrazzi continues by emphasizing the effectiveness of virtual teams, “A 2009 study of 80 global software teams by authors from BCG and WHU-Otto Beisheim School of Management indicates that well-managed dispersed teams can actually outperform those that share office space” (Ferrazzi, Harvard Business Review). The key concept of Ferrazzi’s article is the importance of effectively managing virtual teams. Successful management of virtual teams can bring great profit to organizations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;arguments-against-virtual-teams&quot;&gt;Arguments against virtual teams&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Human interaction is critical to the development of people and ideas. Comradery brings teams closer together, enabling vulnerable trust and understanding. This is an aspect that virtual teams lack to truly embrace the power of team work. “Virtual teams lack the informal, everyday conversations that co-located employees take for granted – sharing information at the water cooler, solving problems on the coffee run” (Bailey, Forbes). This type of interaction is something I see as critical to innovation within teams, which is something that lacks in virtual teams. Though different cultural differences bring different forms of problem solving abilities to a team, they also come with negative outcomes if not addressed properly. For example, cultural differences in communication and what is recognized as offensive or rude: “Miscommunication is rife in virtual teams; even more so when the team spans cultures. A message that seems succinct to a team member in Tel Aviv comes across rude to an employee in Washington, while the American’s would-be polite message (‘thank you in advance…’) seems insipid to their Israeli counterpart.” (Bailey, Forbes). Leaders of virtual teams should be aware of all team members culture and identify cultural differences as well as possible issues with communication. Addressing cultural differences in communication is critical to maximizing team performance. Understanding of the team’s culture should be done prior to working on tasks to spot cultural differences within the team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-i-would-use-virtual-teams&quot;&gt;How I would use virtual teams&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the technology industry continues to evolve, virtual teams will become an even more critical component to organization’s success. “In a geographically distributed team, trust is measured almost exclusively in terms of reliability” (Meyer, Forbes). One of the features of virtual teams that I will implement at work is trust and reliability. One of the training courses I participated at Esri – Inspiring Trust – had a tremendous impact on the virtual teams I’m currently working with. It allowed me to clarify objectives, show integrity and intent, which conceives trust and shows my commitment to the team’s goals. The main principle I obtained from my training was: if there is trust within the the team, then everyone can function more consistently and effectively.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another useful benefits of having virtual teams addressed in the articles was effective collaboration on projects and reducing costs. These principle of reducing cost (real estate &amp;amp; buildings) happens naturally in virtual teams in different time zones. What I can continue to apply is the principle of effective communication within virtual teams. The more effective the communication, the more precise and effective the team can be in completing objectives. Communication is one of the core and key concepts I learned from my research, which will yield immensely positive and effective results. “Teams’ communication and work reports are available online to facilitate swift responses to the demands of the (global) market.” (Chand, yourarticlelibrary.com). From Chand’s claims, virtual reports and communication work as a very effective way to quickly react and adapt to market changes or conditions with little to no lag time. Something as simple as an instant message, which is delivered instantly to teammates. This quick communication acts as an optimal tool for virtual team performance maximization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, virtual teams will continue to be a vital source or production in the software industry. I’ve had great experiences working in virtual teams and a few bad ones. These articles helped me further my knowledge in ways to maintain and sustain virtual teams and for them to remain effective and efficient. In this essay I’ve reviewed what virtual teams are and how they affect many software developers working across continents. Next I reviewed some of the pros and cons of virtual teams and how they can affect the moral, satisfaction and effectiveness of teams. Finally, I discussed some of my experiences with virtual teams. Moreover, how I can implement my research into virtual teams that I work with now and virtual teams that I’ll work with in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bailey, Sebastian (2013). How To Beat The Five Killers Of Virtual Working. Forbes. Retrieved from: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/sites/sebastianbailey/2013/03/05/how-to-overcome-the-five-major-disadvantages-of-virtual-working/#721d0c0353d7&quot;&gt;http://www.forbes.com/sites/sebastianbailey/2013/03/05/how-to-overcome-the-five-major-disadvantages-of-virtual-working/#721d0c0353d7&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chand, Smriti. Virtual Organisation: Advantages, Disadvantages and Features. yourarticlelibrary.com. Retrieved from: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://www.yourarticlelibrary.com/organization/virtual organisation-advantages-disadvantages-and-features/35535/&quot;&gt;http://www.yourarticlelibrary.com/organization/virtual organisation-advantages-disadvantages-and-features/35535/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ferrazzi, Keith (2014). Getting Virtual Teams Right. Harvard Business Review. Retrieved from: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;https://hbr.org/2014/12/getting-virtual-teams-right&quot;&gt;https://hbr.org/2014/12/getting-virtual-teams-right&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meyer, Erin (2010). The Four Keys To Success With Virtual Teams. Forbes. Retrieved from: &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://www.forbes.com/2010/08/19/virtual-teams-meetings-leadership managing-cooperation.html&quot;&gt;http://www.forbes.com/2010/08/19/virtual-teams-meetings-leadership managing-cooperation.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/12/27/virtual-teams/</id>
      <updated>2016-12-27T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Julio Ochoa</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>Chaos Theory and Organizational Strategy </title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/20/virtual-chaos-theory/" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;“One of the enduring problems facing the field of strategic management is the lack of theoretical tools available to describe and predict the behavior of firms and industries” (Levy, 1994, p. 167), a powerful statement presented by Levy for firms operating in the twenty-first century. As firms continue to grow and develop, the organization system becomes more complex and unpredictable. In this article, I will explain the concept of chaos theory and how it affects organizations. Furthermore, I will present the pros and cons of chaos theory in management and the overall impact of the decision-making process. Lastly, I will discuss how chaos theory and strategy impacts me and how I can utilize this theory to benefit my understanding of corporate systems and methods of operation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;what-is-chaos-theory&quot;&gt;What is chaos theory?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In short, chaos theory is the study of complex, nonlinear, dynamic systems. The most common statement associated with chaos theory states, “It’s poetic, the notion that the flap of a butterfly’s wing in Brazil can set off a cascade of atmospheric events that, weeks later, spurs the formation of a tornado in Texas” (Wolchover, 2011). In this case, the attribution to weather pattern and its unpredictability has an Infinitum source of association, which makes it practically impossible to predict weather patterns more than a few days out. There is an unmeasurable amount of components that affect the weather, which in turn affects the forecasting abilities for meteorologists to make accurate predictions. In contrast to weather patterns, tossing a coin or rolling a die are deterministic systems, but still, produce a random outcome. If we go into further details of tossing a coin, chaos theory suggests that are infinitum ways to flip a coin. Moreover, Levy states, “Not only is it impossible to toss a coin twice in exactly the same way but on each toss the coin is subject to slightly different air currents, themselves a result to turbulent air flow” (Levy, 1994, p. 168).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we conceptualize organizations, corporations, and industries as complex, dynamic nonlinear systems, then we can apply the concepts of chaos theory to our everyday jobs as managers. Corporations interact with each other constantly, whether it’s vendors, suppliers or direct competition. According to Levy all of the interactions corporations participate in are strategic in the sense that decisions by one corporations take into account anticipated reactions by others (Levy, 1994, p170). Therefore, corporate macro and micro action will be interdependence. In chaos theory, small disturbances in one corporation multiply over time in a nonlinear fashion. Consequently, the initial action might affect other corporations. In chaos theory one can’t account for every single variable affecting the organization, this makes forecasting and long term planning difficult to achieve. Traditional concepts and paradigms of strategy suggest that small changes in parameters should lead to correspondingly small changes in the equilibrium outcome. Chaos theory contradicts this concept and forces us to analyze how small changes can produce enormous consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chaos-theory-pros&quot;&gt;Chaos theory pros&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I view as a benefit to chaos theory is the depth of understanding. Chaos theory forces us to step back and look at the bigger picture and assess if other variables are affecting our outcome, whether big or small. Though in the case of a butterfly in Brazil flapping its wing causes a tornado in Texas is a bit far-fetched, other sources might be obtainable like how is the competition in another country affecting our domestic sales. A more detailed analysis could be a competitor missing its production output deadline for a quarter. Therefore, they did not have enough supply causing their customers to buy from us (the competitor). This, in turn, might cause our organization to believe internal sources caused the increase in sales when in fact it was a competitor error that increased sales. In this example, increased sales should be attributed to external factors, which at times can be chaotic. I see the concept of chaos theory as extremely valuable to the organization, as there are thousands of variables in play, which affect an overall system. In my opinion, the more variables we can account for, the more control we have, causing more accurate forecasting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;chaos-theory-cons&quot;&gt;Chaos theory cons&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Chaos theory has a far reach when it comes to actions and reaction, which is very difficult to find the initial source of the result. According to Levy, “The size of fluctuations from one period to the next in chaotic systems vary in size” (Levy, 1994, 171), suggesting that managers might underestimate the potential for large changes in industry conditions or competitors’ behavior. A big negative feature of chaos theory is predictability. It’s difficult to determine how the outcome was achieved when other factors outside of our control have influence in results, which can make it difficult to reproduce effective results. How much do we attribute from our skills and knowledge and how much do we attribute t the randomness of other components outside of our immediate environment to our results? Chaos theory doesn’t give us much information as to distribution and impact of outside variables affecting our outcomes. The more variables there are in play, the more subject our outcome is to chaos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;how-i-would-use-it&quot;&gt;How I would use it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From my initial analysis it’s apparent that chaos theory is very complex. It is one way of looking at organization, which are dynamic, complex and nonlinear. I will use the chaos theory model at work and at home to find sources of results and outcomes. I believe it will help me look at results in a different perspective, it will help me step back and look at other components which are helping or hindering my desired outcome. From understanding chaos theory, I will attempt to reduce the amount of components and variables inside systems, so that there is less room for chaotic events, which in turn will affect other components and in turn the system. Another positive concept of chaos they that I find useful is patterns. Chaos theory is subject to produce patterns, but rarely are they exact replicas or duplicates, which at times make it difficult to spot reoccurring events and the differences they have. As a manager I will need to understand how teams work as a unit and how they each attribute to the overall team and how a little effect such as a team member getting a flat tire will affect a project outcome. I find chaos theory very interesting and I will continue to research and understand this concept which accounts for so many unknown variables.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;summary&quot;&gt;Summary&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In summary, I’ve reviewed the concept of chaos theory: the study of complex, nonlinear, dynamic systems and the capacity at which they function. Furthermore, I explained how chaos theory affects organizational strategy, overall performance and outcomes, which is implemented industry wide. Next, I reviewed the pros and cons of chaos theory, from being aware of external components of the system and how they affect outcomes, to the negative feature of unpredictability in chaos. Finally, I talked about how I can apply the concepts of chaos theory into my workplace.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;references&quot;&gt;References:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Levy, David. (1994). Chaos Theory and Strategy: Theory, Application, and Managerial Implications. Strategic Management Journal, Vol. 15, 167 – 178&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wolchover, Natalie. (2011) Can a Butterfly in Brazil Really Cause a Tornado in Texas? live science. Retrieved from &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://www.livescience.com/17455-butterfly-effect-weather-prediction.html&quot;&gt;http://www.livescience.com/17455-butterfly-effect-weather-prediction.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Mendelson, Jonathan and Blumenthal, Elana (2003) Chaos Theory and Fractals. tnellen. Retrieved from &lt;a target=&quot;_blank&quot; rel=&quot;noopener noreferrer&quot; href=&quot;http://www.tnellen.com/alt/chaos.html&quot;&gt;http://www.tnellen.com/alt/chaos.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/12/20/virtual-chaos-theory/</id>
      <updated>2016-12-20T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Julio Ochoa</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
    <entry>
      <title>What's this all about!?</title>
      <link href="http://localhost:4000/2016/12/05/why-blog/" />
      <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Before graduate school I didn’t do much writing. Now, one year into the program, I write about 10 pages per week and read a few chapters from 800 page traditional school books. Yes, I know, it sounds miserable doesn’t it? However, I’ve now grown to love writing and expressing my ideas and concepts through story telling, which would not have happened if I didn’t go to graduate school. How did I end up in graduate school? Esri (the company I work for) awarded me with a fellowship, which includes full tuition coverage, text books and other school expenses. The University of Redlands is not cheap! I am grateful for Esri’s belief in my abilities and what I can contribute to the organization in the future. Anyways, that’s how I ended up here, writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have a bachelors degree in design, in combination with my current MBA studies I plan on combining business and design – hence the title of this blog, The Business of Design. Currently I observe that most companies struggle with a disjointed channel of communication between these two mediums. This is where I plan to emphasis my efforts, bridging the gap of communication between business professionals (executives) and designers/developers (artists and math geniuses).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this blog I will be writing about design, technology, business, and so much more. Anything I see as valuable I plan to share with my readers, weather that be management techniques, new design trends, chaos theory, game theory or organizational behaviour. I will also write about books I’m reading and experiences in the workplace. The product/software industry is hot at the moment and I don’t see it cooling down anytime soon. Products/apps are everywhere and the Internet of Things is just a beginning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope that you find this blog helpful, and if not then hey – at least it helps me with writing and documenting my ideas on the ever growing place called the world wide web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;– Julio&lt;/p&gt;
</summary>
      <id>http://localhost:4000/2016/12/05/why-blog/</id>
      <updated>2016-12-05T00:00:00-08:00</updated>
      <author>
        <name>Julio Ochoa</name>
      </author>
    </entry>
  
</feed>
